JUAN CARLOS URCIA BAREA

jcurciabarea@gmail.com · www.jcurciabarea.info

I am a motivated, diligent analyst with a passion for macroeconomics, finance, and political economy. My current work at Moody's centers on sovereign risk for governments in Latin America. I previously served as policy advisor to U.S. Senator Ben Cardin in Washington, DC. My skillset centers on economic and policy analysis, communication and teamwork, and constantly learning.

EDUCATION

Princeton University Princeton, NJ

August 2020 to May 2022 Master in Public Affairs | School of Public and International Affairs

Brown University Providence, RI Bachelor of Arts | History August 2013 to May 2017

EMPLOYMENT

New York, NY Moody's Corporation July 2022 to Present

Ratings Associate | Sovereign Risk Group

Analyze credit risk and manage ratings of issuers including Argentina, Costa Rica, Guatemala, Panama, Honduras, and Inter-American Development Bank (IADB) focusing on economics, finance, and politics.

- Write research publications covering relevant credit developments, long format credit profiles, ad-hoc pieces and FAQs, and contribute to semi-annual outlook reports for frontier markets and MDBs.
- Communicate with government and multilateral officials, investors, and other stakeholders to coordinate on projects, gather information, and explain company views on credit risks and recent developments.
- Elevated to informal lead analyst for Honduras and Guatemala, with significant involvement following the two countries and leading research pieces, forming recommendations for senior staff and rating committees.
- Selected to help conduct initial research, analysis, and credit rating recommendation for a new frontier market sovereign; nominated to help lead ESG taskforce to assess and improve consistency of assigned scores.
- Organized and participated in trips to IMF spring meetings, IADB meeting, and visits to issuer countries.
- Use software including Excel, Bloomberg, Haver Analytics, and FactSet to conduct in-depth financial and economic analysis, build databases, and create data visualizations.

US Department of Commerce

Princeton, NJ

Graduate Consultant | Office of the US Secretary of Commerce

August 2021 to January 2022

- Graduate capstone project to advise the Office of the Secretary on implementation of the CHIPS Act and how to design and leverage the National Semiconductor Technology Center (NSTC).
- Researched industry trends; interviewed Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturing Company, Intel, academics, researchers, and defense analysts to gather information; organized class trip to Phoenix, Arizona.

US Department of the Treasury

Washington, DC

Graduate Intern | Office of International Financial Markets

May to August 2021

- Created a large database and heatmap dashboard in Excel tracking macroeconomic and financial risk indicators across various advanced economies and emerging markets, using source data from Haver Analytics.
- Wrote and circulated internal memos researching and summarizing theoretical macro-financial concepts such as sovereign-bank debt risks, housing market trends, sovereign dollar debt crises, and credit bubbles.

US Senator Benjamin L. Cardin

Washington, DC

Legislative Correspondent

July 2018 to July 2020 September 2017 to June 2018

Staff Assistant

- Assisted in writing and managing legislation, including the Government Employee Fair Treatment Act (P.L.116-1), which became law guaranteeing back-pay for furloughed workers during government shutdowns.
- Led office research and recommendations on the 2018-2019 35-day federal government shutdown and COVID-19 unemployment insurance and state fiscal relief legislative efforts as part of the CARES Act.
- Researched and wrote recommendation memos for bills, resolutions, nominations, Dear Colleague letters, constituent issues, breaking developments, and other action items for the Senator.

US Senate Committee on Foreign Relations

Intern | Ranking Member, Democratic Staff

July to August 2016

Washington, DC

- Researched and circulated press clips on Southeast Asia security and foreign aid issues.
- Prepared briefing materials for staff and committee members for hearings, meetings, and events.

US Representative David N. Cicilline

Pawtucket, RI

Intern | Pawtucket District Office

May to July 2016

- Managed busy front office, organized and supervised district events, and logged constituent correspondence.
- Created an Excel database for major government and elected officials in Rhode Island for internal office use.

The Walt Disney Company

Burbank, CA

Intern | Corporate Strategy and Business Development

June to August 2015

- Conducted a financial analysis of a merger between two telecommunications firms.
- Collaborated on group research and slide deck on the "smart" ad tech industry landscape.

VOLUNTEERING AND COMMUNITY ACTIVITIES

Instituto Cervantes | Member and Student (2023-Present)

Study the Spanish language and participate in Spanish and Latin American cultural events and activities.

Volunteer Income Tax Assistance (VITA) | SPIA Chapter Co-Lead and Volunteer (2021-2022)

• Provided weekly tax filing services to low-income and disadvantaged residents of Mercer County, New Jersey.

SPIA First Generation and Low-Income (FLI) Students | Co-Lead and Co-Founder (2020-2022)

• Hosted FLI alumni for career talks and collaborate with university on programming for FLI students.

The Julis-Rabinowitz Center for Public Policy and Finance | Graduate Associate (2020-2022)

• Engaged in seminars on financial policy and economic history led by faculty and visiting experts.

LANGUAGES AND NATIONALITIES

- English: Native/Fluent | Spanish: Advanced (C1) | Japanese: Elementary
- United States of America (citizen) | Spain (citizen)

RELEVANT GRADUATE COURSEWORK

Economics and Finance Microeconomics — Professor Amy Craft Macroeconomics — Professor Gregor Jarosch Public Economics — Professor Henrik Kleven International Economics — Professor Silvia Weyerbrock Financial Management — Professor Adam Shrager Growth, Finance, Crises — Professor Ashoka Mody Macroeconomic Ideas — Professor Ashoka Mody Central Banking — Professor Alan Blinder Global Supply Chains — Professor Doyle Hodges

Statistics

Quantitative Analysis – Professor David Lee Econometrics I – Professor Jordan Matsudaira Econometrics II – Professor Alexandre Mas Program & Policy Evaluation – Professor Jean Grossman

Politics

Politics of Public Policy – Professor Andrew Moravcsik Domestic Politics – Professor Frances Lee The State – Professor Philip Pettit

SKILLS AND INTERESTS

Professional: politics, economics, financial analysis, fiscal and debt metrics, statistical analysis, data visualization, graphic design, writing, editing, public speaking, event planning, customer service

Software: Microsoft Office (Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Outlook); Adobe Creative Suite (Photoshop, InDesign); Econometric Analysis (Stata, R); Financial Research (Bloomberg Terminal, Haver Analytics, FactSet, Reuters); Programming (Python, Java, HTML/CSS); Communications (Slack, Signal, Zoom, Webex, Teams)

Policy: macroeconomics, fiscal and monetary policy, financial markets, banking, international affairs, globalization, poverty alleviation and social safety net, labor and unions, wealth and income inequality

Interests: photography, drawing, sudoku, computers, economics, politics, history, hiking, tennis, soccer